Guide to the Donald Wing Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Donald Wing papers
1936-1972
OSB MSS 166
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
9.21
(10 boxes)
The Donald Wing Papers consist of professional and editorial correspondence files, typescripts, and galleys mostly related to his research for and publication of A Short-Title Catalogue of Books Printed in England, Scotland, Ireland, Wales and British America and of English Books Printed in Other Countries, 1641-1700.
Wing, Donald Goddard, 1904-1972
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the Short Title Catalogue Project office, Yale University Library, 2001.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Donald Goddard Wing, 1904-1972
Donald Goddard Wing was born in Athol, Massachusetts in 1904 and attended public schools there. He graduated from Yale University in 1926 and received a master's degree in English from Harvard University in 1928. In that year, he joined the Yale University Library as an assistant reference librarian, and participated in the move of the Yale collections to the new Sterling Memorial Library. Wing spent his entire career at Yale as a librarian and bibliographer, retiring as Associate Librarian for Collections in 1970. He received his Ph.D. from Yale in 1932, was awarded a Guggenheim Fellowship for his bibliographical research in 1935, and was the first Yale librarian to be awarded a research sabbatical, in 1967-68.
Wing is best known for his multi-volume A Short-Title Catalogue of Books Printed in England, Scotland, Ireland, Wales and British America and of English Books Printed in Other Countries, 1641-1700 (Wing), first published in 1945-51 and revised and enlarged in subsequent decades. While the work has been criticized, particularly for Wing's decision to alter entry numbers in the later editions, it has become the standard bibliography in its field. In 1967 Wing published A Gallery of Ghosts: Books Published Between 1641-1700 Not Found in the Short-Title Catalogue, listing more than five thousand titles Wing had found in biliographies, booksellers' lists, or auction catalogues but had been unable to verify.
Donald Wing married Charlotte Farquhar in 1930 and the couple had two children, Robert and Cathy. He died at his home in Woodbridge, Connecticut on October 8, 1972.
Scope and Contents
The Donald Wing Papers consist of correspondence, notes, typescripts and galley proofs mostly relating to Wing's work on the Short-Title Catalogue of Books Printed in England, Scotland, Ireland, Wales and British America and of English Books Printed in Other Countries, 1641-1700. The collection also contains a typescript of his A Gallery of Ghosts.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Professional Files, 1936-1972. II. Short-Title Catalogue Papers.
Bibliographers; Bibliography; Early printed books -- 17th century -- Union lists; English imprints -- Union lists; English literature -- Early modern, 1500-1700 -- Bibliography; Wing, Donald Goddard, 1904-1972; Wing, Donald Goddard, 1904-1972 ( Short-title catalogue); Yale University. Library
- Professional Files, 1936-1972; Series I; 2.21; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Material is arranged in no particular order.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains professional and scholarly correspondence, notes and other material, mostly relating to Wing's work on the Short-Title Catalogue.
  - STC correspondence and papers, 1939-1968; 33 (Box 1)
  - Personal correspondence and papers, 1952-1968; 8 (Box 1)
  - STC correspondence and papers, 1966-1972; 5 (Box 2)
  - Personal correspondence and papers, 1969-1972; 3 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1936-1972; 11 (Box 2)
  - General library files, 1953-1969; 12 (Box 2)
  - General library files, 1949-1971; 2 (Box 3)
- Short-Title Catalogue Papers, [circa 1940-1967]; Series II; 7; (7 boxes)
  The series contains notes, typescripts and galley proofs of volumes of the Short-Title Catalogue, as well as a typescript of A Gallery of Ghosts.
  - A Gallery of Ghosts typescript, undated; 1 (Box 4)
  - 1st edition proofs and miscellaneous material, undated; 11 (Box 4)
  - 2nd edition volume I galley proofs, undated; 10 (Box 5)
  - 2nd edition volume I page proofs, undated; 10 (Box 6)
  - 2nd edition volume I typescripts, undated; 15 (Box 7)
  - 2nd edition volume II galley proofs, undated; 4 (Box 8)
  - 2nd edition volume II proofs, undated; 5 (Box 8)
  - 2nd edition volume II preparations, undated; 9 (Box 9)
  - 2nd edition volume II typescripts, undated; 6 (Box 9)
  - 2nd edition volume II typescripts, undated; 3 (Box 10)
  - 2nd edition volume II manuscripts, undated; 6 (Box 10)